Guide to the Duke University Libraries Collection of Haggadot, 1200-2003 (bulk1900-2003)
Duke University Libraries Collection of Haggadot 1200-2003 (bulk 1900-2003
Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
436 Items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Duke University Libraries Collection of Haggadot consists of items found in the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, the Divinity School Library, Perkins Library, and Lilly Library.
Historical Note
The Haggadah, a liturgical work used in Jewish homes around the world for the yearly Passover celebration, is the most widely published Jewish liturgical book and has appeared in countless forms over the years. Around 40 pages in length, the Haggadah's traditional text is in Hebrew but is often accompanied by translations into the vernacular or occasionally appears only in the vernacular. Thousands of extant editions have been cataloged, and many more uncatalogued editions come to light each year in addition to new editions which are continually being published. Haggadot have been printed in nearly every country where Jews have lived and in nearly every language Jews have spoken.
Collection Overview
The Duke University Libraries Collection of Haggadot consists mainly of Passover Haggadot (singular: Haggadah) from the past 1000 years. The 436 Haggadot in the collection, which are found in the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, the Divinity School Library, Perkins Library, and Lilly Library, span 800 years (1200-2003), represent five continents (excluding only Australia and Antarctica), are written in several different languages (including Russian, Marathi, Italian, Yiddish, Ladino and Arabic), and were created for a variety of specific purposes. A majority of the Haggadot were published in the 20th century. A large number of the Haggadot are illustrated or illuminated while others contain only the text. Although the majority of the Haggadot in the collection were created by printing press, or other printing methods, Duke does own a number of limited edition facsimile editions of handwritten manuscripts. Most, but not all, of the Haggadot found in the Special Collections Library come from the Abram and Frances Pascher Kanof Collection of Jewish Art, Archaeology, and Symbolism. This guide does not include the Duke University Libraries' collection of microfilmed Haggadot. See the last paragraph of the Processing and Searching Note below for further information on searching for Haggadot in the library.
Since many of the Haggadot have similar titles (e.g. Hagadah shel Pesah yields 121 results), and to accommodate the variety of ways in which patrons might want to search for Haggadot, the entire collection has been arranged into three different series: Date List Series, Location List Series, and Purpose List Series. Each of these series contains the entire collection of Haggadot, but arranged according to different criteria. Therefore, the item with call number Haggadah Pam #106, an advertising Haggadah from 19th century New York, can be found in three places: 1) in the Date List under the 19th Century Subseries; 2) in the Location List under the United States Subseries; and 3) in the Purpose List under the Advertising Subseries.
The Date List Series is subdivided by century for Haggadot published from the 13th through the 19th centuries and by decade (e.g., 1910-1919) for those Haggadot created during the 20th and 21st centuries. The majority of the Haggadot (84%) are from the 20th century.
The Location List Series arranges the collection by the country where each Haggadah was created--usually where the item was printed--then by the date of creation. However, facsimile editions have been arranged by the place of their original creation. In these cases, the location where the facsimile was printed is identified in the description of each facsimile. This series is further arranged into subseries by country, including Algeria, Argentina, Austria, Bosnia-Hercegovina, Canada, Czech Republic, England, France, Germany, India, Israel, Italy, Morocco, Netherlands, Poland, Portugal, Russia, Spain, Tunisia, and United States.
The Purpose List Series is further subdivided by the specific purpose for which each Haggadah was written. Most of the Haggadot were created for use at a Passover seder and thus are arranged into the General Subseries. These Haggadot are generally traditional in content and are meant to be used by anyone. Other purpose subseries include Advertising, Children, Christian, Denominations (of Judaism), Facsimiles, Fundraising, Kibbutz, Parody, and Resource.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Conservative Judaism -- Liturgy -- Texts
Early printed books -- 18th century -- Facsimiles
Haggadah
Haggadah -- Bibliography
Haggadah -- Commentaries
Haggadah -- History
Haggadah -- Illustrations
Haggadah -- Influence
Haggadah -- Manuscripts
Haggadah -- Sources
Haggadah -- Texts
Haggadot
Haggadot -- Bibliography
Haggadot -- History
Haggadot -- Texts
Haggadot, Kibbutz
Haggadot, Kibbutz -- Texts
Haggadot, Secular
Haggadot -- Texts
Haggadot, Trade
Illumination of books and manuscripts, Jewish
Judaism -- Liturgy -- Texts
Manuscripts, Hebrew
Manuscripts, Hebrew -- Facsimiles
Passover
Passover -- Customs and practices
Passover -- Prayer-books and devotions
Seder -- Liturgy -- Texts
Contents of Collection
- Date List Series, 1200-2003
  Subdivided by century for Haggadot published from the 13th through the 19th centuries and by decade (e.g. 1910-1919) for those Haggadot created during the 20th and 21st centuries. The majority of the Haggadot (84%) are from the 20th century. Arranged alphabetically within each date subdivision.
  Many Haggadot are dated by Hebrew year, which begins and ends in the Gregorian month of September or October. Therefore, certain Haggadot have a date such as 1909-1910 instead of 1909. Haggadot whose date range covers two subseries can be found in the subseries with the earlier date. Thus, a Haggadah with a date of 1909-1910 is located in the 1900-1909 Subseries, and a Haggadah with a date of 1899-1900 is located in the 19th Century Subseries).
  - 13th Century Subseries, (1 item)
    - The Birds Head Haggada of the Bezalel National Art Museum in Jerusalem / Facsimile volume printed in collotype by Kunstanstalt Max Jaffé in Vienna, 13th Century., 29 cm. Illuminated.
      Location: Germany
      Facsimile printed in 1965. Commentary volume included. Oldest surviving Ashkenazi illuminated Haggadah manuscript named for its illustrations of human figures with pronounced birds' heads. Signed by a scribed named Menahem.
  - 14th Century Subseries, (4 items)
    - The Barcelona Haggadah: an illuminated Passover compendium from 14th-Century Catalonia in facsimile (MS British Library Additional 14761) / edited by Jeremy Schonfield; with translations of poems and Targumim by Raphael Loewe; other translations by David Goldstein and Jeremy Schonfield; and contributions by Malachi Beit-Arié .., 14th Century., 27 cm. Illuminated.
      Location: Catalonia
      Facsimile printed in 1992. Commentary volume included. Illuminations include images of medieval Spanish homes, synagogues and musical instruments. Early owners of the Haggadah are identified by signatures as is the 16th Century ecclesiastical censor Visto per me Fra. Luigi del Ordine de San Dominico.
    - The Sarajevo Haggadah. Text by Cecil Roth, 14th Century., 23 cm. Illustrated.
      Location: Northern Spain
      Facsimile published in New York in 1966. English introduction by Cecil Roth. Consists of 34 full-page miniatures, an illuminated Haggadah text, and hymns and Torah readings for the Passover week. Signed in 1609 by Giovanni Domenico, a church censor. Named because of its location in the Sarajevo Museum. This Haggadah was almost destroyed during the bombardment of Sarajevo in 1994 but was saved by two staff members of the demolished museum where it was housed.
    - The Kaufmann Haggadah, 14th Century., 27 cm. Illuminated.
      Location: Spain
      Facsimile printed in Budapest, Hungary in 1957. Includes 14 full page miniatures and a decorated text.
    - The Sarajevo Haggadah. Text by Cecil Roth, 14th Century., 23 cm. Illustrated.
      Facsimile of the Sarajevo Haggadah from the 14th Century in Northern Spain. Published in New York in 1966. English introduction by Cecil Roth. Consists of 34 full-page miniatures, an illuminated Haggadah text, and hymns and Torah readings for the Passover week. Named because of its location in the Sarajevo Museum.
  - 15th Century Subseries, (3 items)
    - The Washington Haggadah: a facsimile edition of an illuminated fifteenth-Century Hebrew manuscript at the Library of Congress / signed by Joel ben Simeon; edited by Myron M. Weinstein, 1478., 28 cm. Illuminated.
      Location: Italy
      Facsimile printed in 1991. Commentary volume included. Signed by 15th Century scribe and artist, Joel ben Simeon. A number of pages contain wine stains as well as notes written in the margins. It is known as the Washington Haggadah because of its location at the Library of Congress in Washington D.C.
    - The Rylands Haggadah: a medieval Sephardi masterpiece in facsimile: an illuminated Passover compendium from mid-14th-Century Catalonia in the collections of the John Rylands University Library of Manchester, with a commentary and a cycle of poems / [introduction, notes on the illuminations, transcription, and English translation by Raphael Loewe], 15th Century., 34 cm. Illustrated.
      Facsimile published in New York, 1988. Sephardi text. Commentary by an unidentified author. Introduction in Hebrew and English.
    - Die Darmstädter Pessach-Haggadah: codex orientalis 8 der Landesbibliothek zu Darmstadt aus dem vierzehnten jahrhundert / herausgegeben und erläutert von Bruno Italiener; unter mitwirkung von Aron Freimann, August L. Mayer und Adolf Schmidt; mit einer gesamtbibliographie der illustrierten Haggadah, 15th Century., 29-37 cm. Illuminated.
      Facsimile. Published in Leipzig, Germany, 1927-1928. Written by the scribe Israel ben Meir of Heidelberg. The illuminations reflect contemporary German architecture and dress.
  - 16th Century Subseries, (8 items)
    - Die Pessach-Haggadah des Gerschom Kohen, 1527 [i.e. 1526], 1526., 32 cm. Illustrated.
      Location: Prague
      Reproduction of the Frankfurter Stadtbibliothek copy of the original edition, printed by Gershom ben Solomon ha-Kohen, in Prague in 1526. This reproduction was printed in Berlin, Germany in 1926.
    - The earliest illustrated Haggadah: printed by Gershom Cohen at Prague / discovered and described by Lazarus Goldschmidt, 1526., 29 cm. Illuminated.
      Reproduction published in 1940 in London, England. Translated from the German manuscript by Immanuel Goldschmidt.
    - The Passover Haggadah of Gershom Cohen: printed at Prague, in the year 5287/1527, 1526., 18 cm. Illuminated.
      Facsimile. Published in 1954 in Tel Aviv, Israel. Includes an introduction in English. Oldest known Haggadah printed with woodcuts. The woodcuts were later used in other printed Haggadot. Unique to this Haggadah is the mention of an obscure practice. On p. 36 is a woodcut of a man holding and pointing to a leaf of lettuce. The accompanying note says, It is generally customary that the husband points to his wife because of the Biblical reference that a bad woman is more bitter than death.
    - Hagadah shel Pesah, 1526., 36 cm. Illustrated.
      Facsimile. Printed in New York, 1964. Includes an English introduction.
    - The earliest illustrated Haggadah: printed by Gershom Cohen at Prague / discovered and described by Lazarus Goldschmidt, 1526., 29 cm. Illuminated.
    - Hagadah shel Pesah: Prag 287 = The Passover Haggadah: Prague 1526, 1526., 32 cm. Illustrated.
      Facsimile printed in Jerusalem in 1972.
    - The Ashkenazi Haggadah: a Hebrew manuscript of the mid-15th Century from the collections of the British Library / written and illuminated by Joel ben Simeon, called Feibusch Ashkenazi; with a commentary attributed to Eleazar ben Judah of Worms; introduction, notes on the illuminations, transcription, and English translation by David Goldstein. 16th Century., 39 cm. Illuminated.
      Facsimile printed in 1985 in Tel Aviv. Additional artwork added by a different artist. Includes a transcription of the Hebrew as well as an English translation.
    - The Ashkenazi Haggadah: a Hebrew manuscript of the mid-15th Century from the collections of the British Library / written and illuminated by Joel ben Simeon called Feibusch Ashkenazi; with a commentary attributed to Eleazar ben Judah of Worms; introduction, notes on the illumination, transcription, and English translation by David Goldstein, 16th Century., 39 cm. Illuminated.
      Facsimile was printed in 1985 in New York. Additional artwork added by a different artist. Includes a transcription of the Hebrew as well as an English translation.
  - 17th Century Subseries, (1 item)
    - Seder Hagadah shel Pesah, Venetsyah 369 = The Passover Haggadah, Venice 1609 / mavo me-et Betsal'el Narkis, 1609., 35 cm. Illustrated.
      Location: Venice, Italy
      Facsimile printed in 1974 Jerusalem. The Venice Haggada of 1609: introduction (15 p.) inserted. Translated by Juda-Arie Leon de Modena.
  - 18th Century Subseries, (21 items)
    - Seder Hagadah shel Pesah bi-leshon ha-kodesh uvi-leshon Italyano: `im kamah tsurot `al kol ha-otot veha-moftim asher na`asu la-avotenu be-Mitsrayim, ba-yam uva-midbar ... / ve-gam ba be-tokham pe. Tseli esh ... ve-hu kitsur Zevah Pesah m.h. Rav Don Yitshak Abravan[el] z.l, 1715-1716., 32 cm. Illustrated.
      Hebrew commentary by Abarbanel. Includes the traditional Hebrew text with an Italian translation.
    - Hagadah shel Pesah: Ofenbakh 482 = The Passover Haggadah: Offenbach 1722, 1722., 32 cm. Illustrated.
      Location: Offenbach, Germany
      Facsimile printed in Jerusalem in 1972. Originally published by Yisra'el ben Mosheh
    - Seder Hagadah shel Pesah: im birkhoteha, 1728-1729., 15 cm. Illustrated.
      Location: Amsterdam
      Pocket edition of Haggadah limiting its Yiddish commentary to occasional rubrics. It relies on eye-catching initial letters and woodcuts to make the text come alive. Handwritten note in Hebrew/Yiddish on the inside of the back cover.
    - Hagadah shel Pesah: Ashkenaz, 489 (1729) = Pessach Haggadah: Ashkenaz, 1729, 1729., 31 cm. Illuminated.
      Location: –ttingen, Germany
      Facsimile printed in Tel Aviv in 1985. Text in Hebrew; rubrics in Hebrew and Yiddish. Facsimile of Pessach Haggadah, –ttingen, 1729. Scribe and illustrator: Jacob ben Michael May Segal. Introduction by Chaya Benjamin. Many of the illuminations are based on woodcuts and copper engravings from the printed Haggadot of Venice and Amsterdam.
    - Hagadat Moravyah = The Moravian Haggadah, 1737., 31 cm. Illuminated.
      Facsimile printed in 198-? The Illuminations are based on the well-known Amsterdam engravings with some additions and changes. Also known as the The Alexander Karl Floersheim Haggadah.
    - Hagadah shel Pesah: Altona, Ashkenaz, 498 (1738) / katav ve-tsayar, Yosef ben David mi-Laypnik = Passover Haggadah: Altona, Germany, 1738 / scribe, illustrator Joseph ben David of Leipnik, 1738., 34 cm. Illustrated.
      Location: Altona, Germany
      Facsimile published in Tel Aviv in 1987. Includes an abbreviation of the Zevah Pesah commentary by Isaac Abravanel as well as a short mystical commentary. Ashkenazi and Sephardi rites included. Includes a separate introduction in Hebrew and English.
    - Hagadat Kopenhagen 499: faksimilah = Copenhagen Haggadah: facsimile, 1739., 33 cm. Illuminated.
      Location: Altona-Hamburg, Germany
      Facsimile printed in Tel Aviv in 1986. The Artist is Uri Pheibush [Philip Isac Levy]. Introduction by Chaya Benjamin. Hebrew and English (12 p.) inserted.
    - Hagadah Seder shel Pesah, 1740-1741., 31 cm. Illustrated.
      Location: Fuerth, Germany
      Yiddish and Hebrew. Includes a list of laws for Passover. Contains many woodcuts as well as artistic initial letters with leaves growing from them. Wine stains throughout.
    - Hagadah shel Pesah / [`orekh u-mehkar, Nahman Ran, `orekhet mishneh, Nivah Penai] = Passover Haggadah / [editor and research, Nachman Ran, assist. editor, Niva Panai], 1751., 28 x 329 cmfolded to 28 x 12 cm. Illustrated.
      Facsimile of The Altona-Hamburg Haggadah. Manuscript. 1751 (Codex Levy 22). Published in Tel Aviv in 1986. English and Hebrew. Map of the Land of Israel, drawn by Abraham Bar-Yaacov, the first Hebrew-letter printed map, attached to the Amsterdam Haggadah from 1696 found on pp. 27-30. By the Scriber ... Uri Feivisch, son of Rabbi Itzhak Eizik ....
    - Hagadah shel Pesah / ['orekh u-mehkar, Nahman Ran, 'orekhet mishneh, Nivah Penai] = Passover Haggadah / [editor and research, Nachman Ran, assist. editor, Niva Panai], 1751., 28 x 329 cmfolded to 28 x 12 cm. Illustrated.
    - Seder Hagadah shel Pesah, 1757-1758., 24 cm. Illustrated.
      Ladino and Hebrew. Includes the evening service for the first days of Passover.
    - Seder Hagada le-Fesah, 1764-1765., 21 cm. Illustrated.
      Includes a short version of Isaac Abarbanel's Zevah Pesah commentary. Wine stains throughout.
    - Passover Haggada: Germany, 1768 / scribe/illustrator, Nathan ben Abraham Speyer of Breslau; collection of the Jewish National and University Library, Jerusalem, Ms. Heb. 8vo 2340 = Hagadah shel Pesah: Ashkenaz, 528 (1768) / katav ve-tsiyer Natan ben Avraham Shpaiyer mi-Bresla; osef Bet ha-sefarim ha-le'umi veha-universita'i, Yerushalayim, ketav-yad 8vo 2340, 1768., 30 cm. Illuminated.
      Location: Breslau, Germany
      Facsimile published in Tel Aviv in 1984. Text in Hebrew; rubrics in Yiddish. Accompanied by introductory material in Hebrew and English, including bibliographies, prepared by Chaya Benjamin.
    - Seder Hagadah shel Pesah, 1779-1780., 17 cm. Illustrated.
      Location: London, England
    - Hagadah Seder shel Pesah, 1782-1783., 31 cm. Text only.
      Text and commentary in Hebrew; ceremonial directions in Yiddish. Includes commentary by Isaac Abarbanel. Wine stains throughout.
    - Helek rishon mi-Sefer arba' yesodot, 1782-1783., 23 cm. Text only.
      Text and commentaries in Hebrew; ceremonial directions in Yiddish. Signed on 1st page by Hare Lovy and Leopold Fried. Stamped on 2nd page by Dr. Hinko Urbah. A faded list of names appears in Hebrew and English on the final two pages. Includes the laws for Passover.
    - Sefer hamon hogeg, 1793-1794., 24 cm. Text only.
      Location: Livorno, Italy
      Ladino and Hebrew. Signed on title page by David b. Raphael Mendola. Wine stains throughout.
    - Hagadah shel pesah: ins daytsh, iberzetst und mit nittslikhen anmerkungn ferzehn, 1795., 17 cm. Illustrated.
      Illustrations were made from woodcuts. Commentary by Joel Brill, based on the Berlin Haggadah of 1745.
    - Ma'aleh bet horin, 1795-1796., 23 cm. Text only.
      Location: Dyhernfurth, Germany
      Stamped on first page: Auguste Steinert Berlin. Includes laws for Passover. Some of the text is underlined in pencil and a few marginal notes are written in pencil. Includes commentary by Isaac Abarbanel.
    - Seder Hagadah shel Pesah, 1795-1796., 17 cm. Text only.
      Location: Karlsruhe, Germany
      Ceremonial directions in Yiddish.
    - Seder Hagadah shel Pesah, 1795-1796., 23 cm. Illustrated.
      Location: Pisa, Italy
      Hebrew and Spanish; Spanish is in Hebrew script. Wine stains throughout.
  - 19th Century Subseries, (29 items)
    - Seder agadah shel Pesah, 1805-1806., 19 cm. Illustrated.
      Ladino (in Rashi script) and Hebrew.
    - Agadat arba' Kosot, 1817., 18 cm. Text only.
      Not a Haggadah. Contains special readings for each of the four cups of wine.
    - Compendium orationum = [Seder Hagadah shel Pesah: kefi minhag Ashkenazim] .., 1828., 20 cm. Text only.
      Location: Verona, Italy
      Hebrew text with some Latin on the title page. Primarily text with four simple illustrations: at the beginning, next to the descriptions of the Matzah and Bitter herbs, and after the final song.
    - Seder Hagadah shel Pesah, oder, Fortrag oyf dia beyden erzten abende Pesah, 1829., 17 cm. Text only.
      Hebrew and Yiddish.
    - Seder Hagadah shel Pesah = Service for the two first nights of Passover: in Hebrew and English, according to the custom of the German and Polish Jews / carefully revised and corrected by Isaac Levi .., 1842., 21 cm. Illuminated.
      Contains eight copper plates relating to the service.
    - Hagadah le-lel shikorim, 1849., 19 cm. Text only.
      English title: Haggadah for the Night of Drunks. This is a parody of the Passover Haggadah for use on the holiday of Purim. An example of parodied text: Instead of the son who doesn't know how to ask, this Haggadah has the son who doesn't know how to drink (p. 7). For this son, you are instructed to open his mouth for him. Written by Zevi Hirsch Sommerhausen.
    - Hagadah = Racconto degli avvenimenti memorabili occasionanti la Pasqua / traduzione riveduta e corretta dall' Mayer Randegger, 1851., 21 cm. Text only.
      Location: Vienna, Austria
      Contains the traditional Hebrew text with an Italian translation. Handwritten notes appear throughout in Hebrew (Rashi script), Italian, and Greek. Four handwritten pages, in Hebrew and Italian, were inserted into the beginning of the Haggadah. These pages serve as an annotated table of contents. Signed on the inside of the cover.
    - Sefer Pi ha-medaber: (notarikon perush Hagadah / mi-meni Yosef bar Rabenu David), 1853-1854., 25 cm. Text only.
      Hebrew with commentary in Rashi script. Stampted on title and back pages by the Librairie Hebraique in Djerba, Tunisia. Wine stains appear throughout.
    - Seder ha-hagadah shel Pesah, 1864., 32 cm. Illustrated.
      Location: Trieste, Italy
      Wine stains throughout.
    - [Seder ha-Hagadah le-lele Pesah: `im ha`atakah u-hora'at ha-dinim u-ha-minhagim ba-lashon hollandit] = Hagadah, voordragt op de beide eerste avonden van het Paasch-feest: in het Nederduitsch vertaald en met vele ophelderingen voorzien / door G.A. Parser .., 1864., 17 cm. Text only.
      Hebrew text with Dutch translation and commentary.
    - Hagadah shel Pesah: Tri'esti 624 = The Passover Haggadah: Trieste 1864 / mahadurat Avraham Hai Morpurgo; ha-ilustratsyot `a. y. K. Krikhmayer [sic], 1864., 32 cm. Illustrated.
      Facsimile printed in Jerusalem in 1974.
    - Seder Hagadah shel Pesah, 1868., 23 cm. Text only.
      Location: Vilna, Poland
      Includes ten commentaries by well-known sages. Wine stains throughout.
    - [Hagadah ve-seder shel Pesah] = Form of service for the two first nights of the feast of Passover, 1869., 23 cm. Illustrated.
      Location: New York
      English and Hebrew. Wine stains throughout.
    - Sefer zikrono le-hayyim: le-zikaron ka'iti ha-nes le-mino be-mile de-Agadata lel hitkadesh hag ha-Pesah ... / ve-hu ha-tsa'ir Hayyim ha-kohen .., 1874-1875., 20 cm. Text only.
      Hebrew and Judaeo-Arabic (using Rashi script).